Guide to the James Hazen Hyde Papers 1874-1940, 1953 MS 319
New-York Historical Society
- Series VII. Henry Baldwin Hyde Memorial Books, 1874, 1894, 1899-1900; 7.83 Linear feet in 6 oversize bound volumes
  The series includes six oversize bound volumes of condolence letters and related documents in connection with the death of Henry Baldwin Hyde in 1899. Most of the letters appear to be from agents and others associated with the Equitable in the United States and abroad. The contents of the volumes are:
  Volume I: Opens with a photograph of H.B. Hyde and a few photographs of the casket at the funeral (held at Fifth Avenue Presbyterian) and of the entrance to the Equitable building. Documents that follow include the text of Rev. Van Dyke's eulogy; Board resolutions from the Equitable and other companies/organizations regarding Hyde's death; text of speech by agent Joseph Bowes at an agents convention in July on the subject "What Mr. Hyde Has Done for the Life Insurance Agent"; telegram cables from agents, employees and insurance industry; and calling cards. In addition there is an extract of minutes from the January 1874 Equitable Board meeting with remarks concerning the death of Henry H. Hyde; an 1894 letter from Chauncey Depew to Henry Baldwin Hyde with complimentary remarks; and a 1900 letter to James Hazen Hyde from the Chamber of Commerce thanking him for a portrait of his father.
  Volume II: Includes condolence letters addressed to Mrs. Hyde; these are in alphabetical order, with correspondents A-S in this volume.
  Volume III: Conclusion of letters addressed to Mrs. Hyde. These are followed by letters addressed to James Hazen Hyde, correspondents A-J. Isabella Gardner and William James are two notable names that appear.
  Volume IV: Continues with condolence letters addressed to James Hazen Hyde, correspondents K-S. Notable names are: Adolph Ochs of the New York Times writes of Hyde's support for him and the newspaper; U.S. senator T.C. Platt regrets he cannot attend the funeral; and George B. Post responds to Hyde's request for a meeting to discuss a monument to his father.
  Volume V: Concludes the letters addressed to Hyde, correspondents S-W. Following these are condolence letters addressed to the principal officers of the Equitable (e.g., James Alexander, William McIntyre).
  Volume VI: Concludes the letters addressed to Equitable officers (e.g., George P. Wilson, William Alexander). Includes on page 469 a copy of the outgoing letter Wilson sent to a few correspondents in which he discusses Hyde's final illness.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Volume I is exceptionally oversize and heavy, requiring two people to transport it to the Reading Room. Accordingly, a confirmed appointment is needed to view the volume in order that transport arrangements can be made.
  Gift of James Hazen Hyde, January 17, 1946
  - Memorial Book, Volume I, 1874, 1894, 1899, 1900 (Volume I)
  - Memorial Book, Volume II, 1899 (Volume II)
  - Memorial Book, Volume III, 1899 (Volume III)
  - Memorial Book, Volume IV, 1899 (Volume IV)
  - Memorial Book, Volume V, 1899 (Volume V)
  - Memorial Book, Volume VI, 1899 (Volume VI)
- Series VIII. Photographs and Certificates, circa 1880s-1953; 1.5 Linear feet in two folders (one oversize)
  The series includes a small number of photographs and three certificates. The photographs include one by Peter A. Juley & Sons of an 1859 solicitation letter from Henry Baldwin Hyde requesting that the recipient purchase an insurance policy of the still being formed Equitable; three of Hyde on horseback or in carriages (1899-1903); one of Hyde as a boy in carriage with father in front of their Bay Shore, L.I. home (oversize); one of Henry Baldwin Hyde taken by Pirou of Paris (oversize, circa 1900); five of paintings of Hyde's father (Henry Baldwin Hyde, one oversize), mother (Annie Fitch Hyde), and grandfather (Henry Hazen Hyde); one of the exterior of Hyde's house in Paris when used as Hopital Auxiliaire 79 during World War I; and Hyde in New York with the president of Equitable and the pastor of Fifth Avenue Presbyterian (1950s). There are also photocopies of other photos of carriages; the originals of at least some of these can be found in the Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections' Subject File (PR 68) under the category "TRANSPORTATION - VEHICLES - CARRIAGES AND COACHES."
  Certificates include: diploma from Harvard (1898), diploma from Princeton (1903), commission as Inspector at rank of Captain from American National Red Cross (1918), Foreign Service Certificate from the Red Cross for work as aide to the Commissioner to France from September 1917-February 1919, and recognition from Harvard for Hyde's efforts in promoting relations between Harvard and French universities (1923).
  The items in the series were donated at varous times in the 1940s-1950s by Hyde. The specific dates are noted on the back of most of the items. Items dated 1960 were donated by Hyde's estate.
  - Photographs, circa 1880s-1953 (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Photographs (oversize), circa 1880s-1900 (Folder Oversize-small)
  - Certificates, 1898-1923 (Folder Oversize-small)